in this video we're going to focus on
rotational kinetic energy
so in this problem we need to calculate
the inertia
and the rotational kinetic energy of the
disk
so let's start with the
inertia the inertia of a disk
is equal to one-half
times the mass of the disk
times r-square
so we have the mass of the disk which is
five kilograms
and the radius is 1.3 meters
so it's half times 5
times 1.3 squared
and so the inertia
of the disk is 4.22
kilograms times square meters
now how can we calculate the rotational
kinetic energy of the disk
and how can we derive its equation
so first let's start with the expression
for kinetic energy
which is one-half
mv squared
linear velocity is angular velocity
times the radius
so let's replace the v squared
with omega squared r squared
so now we have one half
m
omega squared r squared
which i'm going to rewrite it as one
half
m r squared times omega squared
and the sum of this quantity m r squared
that's related to the inertia of an
object
so therefore the rotational kinetic
energy
is one half
times the inertia
times omega squared
notice the similarities between this
equation and this equation
so in both cases we still have
the same fraction one half
now instead of
mass we have rotational inertia
and instead of angular i mean linear
speed we have angular speed
so this is the equation that we need to
calculate the rotational kinetic energy
of an object
so the rotational kinetic energy
is this equation as we said before so
let's go ahead and calculate it
so inertia
is 4.225
in this problem
and omega the angular speed is 15
radians per second
so this is going to be
475.3 joules
so that's the rotational kinetic energy
of the disk
number two
a sphere rolls down a 20 degree incline
starting from rest at a height
of 50 meters
how fast will it be moving forward when
it reaches the bottom of the incline
so we need to find the final speed at
this point
how can we do so
the best way to do this is to use
conservation of energy
the sphere currently has potential
energy
and that energy is going to be converted
to translational kinetic energy because
the sphere is moving forward
but also
some of the energy is going to be used
to rotate the sphere
so it's going to go into rotational
kinetic energy
so the potential energy of the sphere
initially is mgh
the kinetic energy of the sphere
is one-half mv squared
and the rotational kinetic energy is one
half
inertia times omega squared
now we don't have the mass of the sphere
which means somehow we need to cancel m
out of the equation
now the inertia of a sphere
is 2 over 5
m r squared
now keep in mind
omega times r is v
so omega squared times r squared is v
squared
so we can replace r squared omega
squared with v squared and we can cancel
the twos
so what we have now is mgh
is equal to one half
mv squared
plus
one over five mv squared
next we need to combine the fractions
one-half plus one-fifth
so let's do that on the side somewhere
one over two plus one over five
to add these two fractions
we need to get common denominators so
let's multiply this fraction by two over
two and the one on the left by five over
five
so it's going to be five over ten
plus two over ten
which is seven over ten
so therefore we have mgh
is equal to 7 over 10
times mv squared
so now we could divide both sides by the
mass
and so what we have left over
is gh
is equal to 7 over 10 times v squared
now let's multiply both sides by 10 over
7.
so on the right side the sevens will
cancel
and the tens will cancel
so what we have now is ten g h divided
by seven
is equal to v squared so v
is the square root of ten g h
over 7.
so now let's plug in the values to get
the final answer
g is 9.8
the height is 50 meters
and so it's going to be the square root
of 10 times 9.8 times 50 divided by 7.
so this should give you a final answer
of 26.5
meters per second
so this is the linear speed
of the sphere
as it rolls down the incline once it
reaches the bottom of the incline
number three
a 20 kilogram solid disk slash pulley
is attached to a hanging 10 kilogram
block
which is released from rest 500 meters
above the ground
how fast will the block be moving just
before it hits the ground
so how can we calculate the final speed
and we're given the mass of the pulley
which is
20 kilograms
so with this information
what can we do to calculate the final
speed just before it hits the ground
now in this problem we're going to do it
two ways
using conservation of energy and using
forces and free body diagrams
so let's start
by setting it up as a conservation of
energy problem
now this block has the ability to fall
the pulley is fixed in place
so because this block can fall it has
potential energy
and as it begins to fall
the potential energy of that block
decreases and that energy is converted
to
the kinetic energy of the block
because the block is going to move down
with a speed
and
this pulley is fixed in place but it has
the ability to rotate
so as this block falls
the pulley will gain rotational kinetic
energy as it begins to spin
the potential energy of the block is mgh
so let's call this lowercase m and the
mass of the pulley or the disc
will be capital m
the kinetic energy of the block is one
half
mv squared
and the rotational kinetic energy of the
disk
is one half
inertia times omega squared
now the inertia of a solid disk
is one half
m r squared
and we know that omega times r is v so r
squared times omega squared must be v
squared so right now we have this
equation
mgh
is one half
mv squared plus one fourth
mv squared
so now let's plug in the data the mass
of the block is 10
times g
times h which is 500
and then that's going to be one half
times the mass of block which is 10
times the v squared
plus one fourth times the mass of the
pulley
times v squared
ten times nine point eight
times five hundred
is forty nine thousand
half of ten is five and 20 divided by 4
is 5 and 5 plus 5
is 10.
so if we divide both sides by 10
we're going to get
4 900 on the left side
v squared on the right side
so now all we need to do is take the
square root
of both sides
so the square root of 4 900
is 70.
so the final speed
is 70 meters per second
so this is the answer
now let's confirm it
using another method
so we're going to use kinematics and
free body diagrams
so what we need to do is calculate the
acceleration of the system
if we could find the acceleration of the
system and knowing the height that it
falls we could easily find the final
speed
so let's focus on calculating the
acceleration of the system
the first method that we can use
is
newton's second law the acceleration is
going to be the net force acting on the
system divided by the total mass of the
system
so the only driving force that we have
is the weight of this block that causes
the system to move down in the negative
y direction
so the weight of that block is going to
be mg
divided by the total mass so that's
going to be the mass of the block plus
the inertial mass of
the disc which is c times m
now because the inertia is one half m r
squared the c value is the one half
in front of the inertia equation for a
solid disk
so c is one half so this is going to be
one half m
so that's the equation for the
acceleration but i'm going to show you
how to derive that equation
using forces and free body diagrams so
i'm just going to rewrite it here just
for reference
since i'm going to need the space on the
right
so this is the equation that we need to
derive
now this block is affected by an upward
tension force
and that tension force which slows down
the block from falling
is the same force that pulls the pulley
down towards the right
and so that tension force creates a
torque
that causes the pulley to rotate
clockwise
so that torque
is a negative torque
so first we need to write an expression
for the net torque acting on
the pulley or the solid disk
so that net torque is equal to this
value so that's negative
t
or negative tau
and this torque is equal to inertia
times alpha
now the net torque acting on the disc is
also moving in the clockwise direction
so that has to be negative as well which
means that these two negative signs will
cancel so
we really don't have to worry about it
in this problem
the inertia of a solid disk is one half
m r squared
and the torque is the tension force
times the radius
so we have a tension force
and r is the moment arm which is the
distance between the axis of rotation
and the line of action of the tension
force or basically where the tension
force is located
so now acceleration is alpha times r and
alpha
is a divided by r
so let's replace alpha
with a over r
so now we could cancel one of the r's on
the left
and so what we have left over is one
half
m r a
which is equal to t r
and then we could cancel r
so let's save this equation
so one half
m a
is equal to the tension force acting on
the pulley
so now let's write
the net force equation for that block
so the net force acting on that block
is equal to the upward tangent force t
minus the downward weight force on that
block which is
mg
now the net force based on newton's
second law
is
now this block is accelerating in the
negative y direction so that's going to
be negative m a
and so that's equal to t minus mg
now to get t by itself
we need to take this term which is
negative on the right side
and move it to the left side where it's
going to become positive
so mg minus ma
is equal to t
now let's replace t
with one half m a
now our goal at this point
is to isolate a
so let's take negative m a and move it
to the right side
so what we have now is mg
is equal to one half
m a
plus lowercase m times a
so now we could factor out a on the
right side
so mg is going to be a
times
one half m
plus m
so solve for a is going to be mg divided
by one half m
plus m
so as you can see these two equations
are equivalent
so now you have two ways in which you
could derive
the equation for the acceleration for
this problem
so now let's go ahead and calculate the
acceleration
so it's mg which is 10 times 9.8
divided by m which is 10
plus one-half the mass of the pulley
which is 20.
10 times 9.8 is 98.
half of 20 is 10 plus another 10 that's
20.
so the acceleration is 9 98 excuse me
divided by 20.
and so that's going to be 4.9 meters per
second squared
so now that we have the acceleration of
the system
we can now find out how fast
the block is going to be moving before
it histogram
the equation that we need
is this equation v final squared is
equal to v initial squared
plus 2ad
now the block is released from rest
which means that the initial speed is 0.
the acceleration of the block
is negative 4.9 meters per second
squared the reason why it's negative is
because it's accelerating in the
negative y direction
now d is the displacement the block is
going down 500 meters
so the displacement in the y direction
is negative 500
so it's going to be 2 times negative 4.9
times negative 500
and so v final squared
is 4 900.
so now we got to take the square root of
both sides
now 4 900 is basically
49 times 100
so this is going to be the square root
of 49 times the square root of 100 the
square root of 49 is 7 and the square
root of 100 is 10
so the square root of 4900 is 70.
so the final speed is going to be 70
meters per second
and so as you can see it's the same
answer as what we had here
so you can solve this problem by taking
a conservation of energy approach
or by
finding the acceleration of the system
and then use kinematics to calculate the
final velocity
you